<div>
  <head>IDLE DAYS ON THE YANN</head>
  <p n="1">
    So I came down through the wood on the bank of Yann and found, as had been
    prophesied, the ship <hi>Bird of the River</hi> about to loose her cable.
  </p>
  <p n="2">
    The captain sat cross-legged upon the white deck with his scimitar lying
    beside him in its jeweled scabbard, and the sailors toiled to spread the
    nimble sails to bring the ship into the central stream of Yann, and all
    the while sang ancient soothing songs. And the wind of the evening
    descending cool from the snowfields of some mountainous abode of distant
    gods came suddenly, like glad tidings to an anxious city, into the
    wing-like sails.
  </p>
  <p n="3">
    And so we came into the central stream, whereat the sailors lowered the
    greater sails. But I had gone to bow before the captain, and to inquire
    concerning the miracles, and appearances among men, of the most holy gods
    of whatever land he had come from. And the captain answered that he came
    from fair Belzoond, and worshipped gods that were the least and humblest,
    who seldom sent the famine or the thunder, and were easily appeased with
    little battles. And I told how I came from Ireland, which is of Europe,
    whereat the captain and all the sailors laughed, for they said, <q>There are
    no such places in all the land of dreams.</q> When they had ceased to mock
    me, I explained that my fancy mostly dwelt in the desert of Cuppar-Nombo,
    about a beautiful blue city called Golthoth the Damned, which was
    sentinelled all round by wolves and their shadows, and had been utterly
    desolate for years and years, because of a curse which the gods once spoke
    in anger and could never since recall. And sometimes my dreams took me as
    far as Pungar Vees, the red walled city where the fountains are, which
    trades with the Isles and Thul. When I said this they complimented me upon
    the abode of my fancy, saying that, though they had never seen these
    cities, such places might well be imagined. For the rest of that evening I
    bargained with the captain over the sum that I should pay him for any fare
    if God and the tide of Yann should bring us safely as far as the cliffs by
    the sea, which are named Bar-Wul-Yann, the Gate of Yann.
  </p>
  <p n="4">
    And now the sun had set, and all the colours of the world and heaven had
    held a festival with him, and slipped one by one away before the imminent
    approach of night. The parrots had all flown home to the jungle on either
    bank, the monkeys in rows in safety on high branches of the trees were
    silent and asleep, the fireflies in the deeps of the forest were going up
    and down, and the great stars came gleaming out to look on the face of
    Yann. Then the sailors lighted lanterns and hung them round the ship, and
    the light flashed out on a sudden and dazzled Yann, and the ducks that fed
    along his marshy banks all suddenly arose, and made wide circles in the
    upper air, and saw the distant reaches of the Yann and the white mist that
    softly cloaked the jungle, before they returned again to their marshes.
  </p>
  <p n="5">
    And then the sailors knelt on the decks and prayed, not all together, but
    five or six at a time. Side by side there kneeled down together five or
    six, for there only prayed at the same time men of different faiths, so
    that no god should hear two men praying to him at once. As soon as any one
    had finished his prayer, another of the same faith would take his place.
    Thus knelt the row of five or six with bended heads under the fluttering
    sail, while the central stream of the River Yann took them on towards the
    sea, and their prayers rose up from among the lanterns and went towards
    the stars. And behind them in the after end of the ship the helmsman
    prayed aloud the helmsman’s prayer, which is prayed by all who follow his
    trade upon the River Yann, of whatever faith they be. And the captain
    prayed to his little lesser gods, to the gods that bless Belzoond.
  </p>
  <p n="6">
    And I too felt that I would pray. Yet I liked not to pray to a jealous God
    there where the frail affectionate gods whom the heathen love were being
    humbly invoked; so I bethought me, instead, of Sheol Nugganoth, whom the
    men of the jungle have long since deserted, who is now unworshipped and
    alone; and to him I prayed.
  </p>
  <p n="7">
    And upon us praying the night came suddenly down, as it comes upon all men
    who pray at evening and upon all men who do not; yet our prayers comforted
    our own souls when we thought of the Great Night to come.
  </p>
  <p n="8">
    And so Yann bore us magnificently onwards, for he was elate with molten
    snow that the Poltiades had brought him from the Hills of Hap, and the
    Marn and Migris were swollen with floods; and he bore us in his full might
    past Kyph and Pir, and we saw the lights of Goolunza.
  </p>
  <p n="9">
    Soon we all slept except the helmsman, who kept the ship in the mid-stream
    of Yann.
  </p>
  <p n="10">
    When the sun rose the helmsman ceased to sing, for by song he cheered
    himself in the lonely night. When the song ceased we suddenly all awoke,
    and another took the helm, and the helmsman slept.
  </p>
  <p n="11">
    We knew that soon we should come to Mandaroon. We made a meal, and
    Mandaroon appeared. Then the captain commanded, and the sailors loosed
    again the greater sails, and the ship turned and left the stream of Yann
    and came into a harbour beneath the ruddy walls of Mandaroon. Then while
    the sailors went and gathered fruits I came alone to the gate of
    Mandaroon. A few huts were outside it, in which lived the guard. A
    sentinel with a long white beard was standing in the gate, armed with a
    rusty pike. He wore large spectacles, which were covered with dust.
    Through the gate I saw the city. A deathly stillness was over all of it.
    The ways seemed untrodden, and moss was thick on doorsteps; in the
    market-place huddled figures lay asleep. A scent of incense came wafted
    through the gateway, of incense and burned poppies, and there was a hum of
    the echoes of distant bells. I said to the sentinel in the tongue of the
    region of Yann, <q>Why are they all asleep in this still city?</q>
  </p>
  <p n="12">
    He answered: <q>None may ask questions in this gate for fear they will wake
    the people of the city. For when the people of this city wake the gods
    will die. And when the gods die men may dream no more.</q> And I began to ask
    him what gods that city worshipped, but he lifted his pike because none
    might ask questions there. So I left him and went back to the <hi>Bird of the
    River</hi>.
  </p>
  <p n="13">
    Certainly Mandaroon was beautiful with her white pinnacles peering over
    her ruddy walls and the green of her copper roofs.
  </p>
  <p n="14">
    When I came back again to the <hi>Bird of the River</hi>, I found the sailors
    were returned to the ship. Soon we weighed anchor, and sailed out again,
    and so came once more to the middle of the river. And now the sun was
    moving toward his heights, and there had reached us on the River Yann the
    song of those countless myriads of choirs that attend him in his progress
    round the world. For the little creatures that have many legs had spread
    their gauze wings easily on the air, as a man rests his elbows on a
    balcony and gave jubilant, ceremonial praises to the sun, or else they
    moved together on the air in wavering dances intricate and swift, or
    turned aside to avoid the onrush of some drop of water that a breeze had
    shaken from a jungle orchid, chilling the air and driving it before it, as
    it fell whirring in its rush to the earth; but all the while they sang
    triumphantly. <q>For the day is for us,</q> they said, <q>whether our great and
    sacred father the Sun shall bring up more life like us from the marshes,
    or whether all the world shall end tonight.</q> And there sang all those
    whose notes are known to human ears, as well as those whose far more
    numerous notes have been never heard by man.
  </p>
  <p n="15">
    To these a rainy day had been as an era of war that should desolate
    continents during all the lifetime of a man.
  </p>
  <p n="16">
    And there came out also from the dark and steaming jungle to behold and
    rejoice in the Sun the huge and lazy butterflies. And they danced, but
    danced idly, on the ways of the air, as some haughty queen of distant
    conquered lands might in her poverty and exile dance, in some encampment
    of the gipsies, for the mere bread to live by, but beyond that would never
    abate her pride to dance for a fragment more.
  </p>
  <p n="17">
    And the butterflies sung of strange and painted things, of purple orchids
    and of lost pink cities and the monstrous colours of the jungle’s decay.
    And they, too, were among those whose voices are not discernible by human
    ears. And as they floated above the river, going from forest to forest,
    their splendour was matched by the inimical beauty of the birds who darted
    out to pursue them. Or sometimes they settled on the white and wax-like
    blooms of the plant that creeps and clambers about the trees of the
    forest; and their purple wings flashed out on the great blossoms as, when
    the caravans go from Nurl to Thace, the gleaming silks flash out upon the
    snow, where the crafty merchants spread them one by one to astonish the
    mountaineers of the Hills of Noor.
  </p>
  <p n="18">
    But upon men and beasts the sun sent drowsiness. The river monsters along
    the river’s marge lay dormant in the slime. The sailors pitched a
    pavilion, with golden tassels, for the captain upon the deck, and then
    went, all but the helmsman, under a sail that they had hung as an awning
    between two masts. Then they told tales to one another, each of his own
    city or of the miracles of his god, until all were fallen asleep. The
    captain offered me the shade of his pavillion with the gold tassels, and
    there we talked for a while, he telling me that he was taking merchandise
    to Perdóndaris, and that he would take back to fair Belzoond things
    appertaining to the affairs of the sea. Then, as I watched through the
    pavilion’s opening the brilliant birds and butterflies that crossed and
    recrossed over the river, I fell asleep, and dreamed that I was a monarch
    entering his capital underneath arches of flags, and all the musicians of
    the world were there, playing melodiously their instruments; but no one
    cheered.
  </p>
  <p n="19">
    In the afternoon, as the day grew cooler again, I awoke and found the
    captain buckling on his scimitar, which he had taken off him while he
    rested.
  </p>
  <p n="20">
    And now we were approaching the wide court of Astahahn, which opens upon
    the river. Strange boats of antique design were chained there to the
    steps. As we neared it we saw the open marble court, on three sides of
    which stood the city fronting on colonnades. And in the court and along
    the colonnades the people of that city walked with solemnity and care
    according to the rites of ancient ceremony. All in that city was of
    ancient device; the carving on the houses, which, when age had broken it,
    remained unrepaired, was of the remotest times, and everywhere were
    represented in stone beasts that have long since passed away from
    Earth—the dragon, the griffin, the hippogriffin, and the different
    species of gargoyle. Nothing was to be found, whether material or custom,
    that was new in Astahahn. Now they took no notice at all of us as we went
    by, but continued their processions and ceremonies in the ancient city,
    and the sailors, knowing their custom, took no notice of them. But I
    called, as we came near, to one who stood beside the water’s edge, asking
    him what men did in Astahahn and what their merchandise was, and with whom
    they traded. He said, <q>Here we have fettered and manacled Time, who would
    otherwise slay the gods.</q>
  </p>
  <p n="21">
    I asked him what gods they worshipped in that city, and he said, <q>All
    those gods whom Time has not yet slain.</q> Then he turned from me and would
    say no more, but busied himself in behaving in accordance with ancient
    custom. And so, according to the will of Yann, we drifted onwards and left
    Astahahn. The river widened below Astahahn, and we found in greater
    quantities such birds as prey on fishes. And they were very wonderful in
    their plumage, and they came not out of the jungle, but flew, with their
    long necks stretched out before them, and their legs lying on the wind
    behind, straight up the river over the mid-stream.
  </p>
  <p n="22">
    And now the evening began to gather in. A thick white mist had appeared
    over the river, and was softly rising higher. It clutched at the trees
    with long impalpable arms, it rose higher and higher, chilling the air;
    and white shapes moved away into the jungle as though the ghosts of
    shipwrecked mariners were searching stealthily in the darkness for the
    spirits of evil that long ago had wrecked them on the Yann.
  </p>
  <p n="23">
    As the sun sank behind the field of orchids that grew on the matted summit
    of the jungle, the river monsters came wallowing out of the slime in which
    they had reclined during the heat of the day, and the great beasts of the
    jungle came down to drink. The butterflies a while since were gone to
    rest. In little narrow tributaries that we passed night seemed already to
    have fallen, though the sun which had disappeared from us had not yet set.
  </p>
  <p n="24">
    And now the birds of the jungle came flying home far over us, with the
    sunlight glistening pink upon their breasts, and lowered their pinions as
    soon as they saw the Yann, and dropped into the trees. And the widgeon
    began to go up the river in great companies, all whistling, and then would
    suddenly wheel and all go down again. And there shot by us the small and
    arrow-like teal; and we heard the manifold cries of flocks of geese, which
    the sailors told me had recently come in from crossing over the Lispasian
    ranges; every year they come by the same way, close by the peak of Mluna,
    leaving it to the left, and the mountain eagles know the way they come
    and—men say—the very hour, and every year they expect them by the same
    way as soon as the snows have fallen upon the Northern Plains. But soon it
    grew so dark that we heard those birds no more, and only heard the
    whirring of their wings, and of countless others besides, until they all
    settled down along the banks of the river, and it was the hour when the
    birds of the night went forth. Then the sailors lit the lanterns for the
    night, and huge moths appeared, flapping about the ship, and at moments
    their gorgeous colours would be revealed by the lanterns, then they would
    pass into the night again, where all was black. And again the sailors
    prayed, and thereafter we supped and slept, and the helmsman took our
    lives into his care.
  </p>
  <p n="25">
    When I awoke I found that we had indeed come to Perdóndaris, that famous
    city. For there it stood upon the left of us, a city fair and notable, and
    all the more pleasant for our eyes to see after the jungle that was so
    long with us. And we were anchored by the market-place, and the captain’s
    merchandise was all displayed, and a merchant of Perdóndaris stood looking
    at it. And the captain had his scimitar in his hand, and was beating with
    it in anger upon the deck, and the splinters were flying up from the white
    planks; for the merchant had offered him a price for his merchandise that
    the captain declared to be an insult to himself and his country’s gods,
    whom he now said to be great and terrible gods, whose curses were to be
    dreaded. But the merchant waved his hands, which were of great fatness,
    showing the pink palms, and swore that of himself he thought not at all,
    but only of the poor folk in the huts beyond the city to whom he wished to
    sell the merchandise for as low a price as possible, leaving no
    remuneration for himself. For the merchandise was mostly the thick
    toomarund carpets that in the winter keep the wind from the floor, and
    tollub which the people smoke in pipes. Therefore the merchant said if he
    offered a piffek more the poor folk must go without their toomarunds when
    the winter came, and without their tollub in the evenings, or else he and
    his aged father must starve together. Thereat the captain lifted his
    scimitar to his own throat, saying that he was now a ruined man, and that
    nothing remained to him but death. And while he was carefully lifting his
    beard with his left hand, the merchant eyed the merchandise again, and
    said that rather than see so worthy a captain die, a man for whom he had
    conceived an especial love when first he saw the manner in which he
    handled his ship, he and his aged father should starve together and
    therefore he offered fifteen piffeks more.
  </p>
  <p n="26">
    When he said this the captain prostrated himself and prayed to his gods
    that they might yet sweeten this merchant’s bitter heart—to his little
    lesser gods, to the gods that bless Belzoond.
  </p>
  <p n="27">
    At last the merchant offered yet five piffeks more. Then the captain wept,
    for he said that he was deserted of his gods; and the merchant also wept,
    for he said that he was thinking of his aged father, and of how he soon
    would starve, and he hid his weeping face with both his hands, and eyed
    the tollub again between his fingers. And so the bargain was concluded,
    and the merchant took the toomarund and tollub, paying for them out of a
    great clinking purse. And these were packed up into bales again, and three
    of the merchant’s slaves carried them upon their heads into the city. And
    all the while the sailors had sat silent, cross-legged in a crescent upon
    the deck, eagerly watching the bargain, and now a murmur of satisfaction
    arose among them, and they began to compare it among themselves with other
    bargains that they had known. And I found out from them that there are
    seven merchants in Perdóndaris, and that they had all come to the captain
    one by one before the bargaining began, and each had warned him privately
    against the others. And to all the merchants the captain had offered the
    wine of his own country, that they make in fair Belzoond, but could in no
    wise persuade them to it. But now that the bargain was over, and the
    sailors were seated at the first meal of the day, the captain appeared
    among them with a cask of that wine, and we broached it with care and all
    made merry together. And the captain was glad in his heart because he knew
    that he had much honour in the eyes of his men because of the bargain that
    he had made. So the sailors drank the wine of their native land, and soon
    their thoughts were back in fair Belzoond and the little neighbouring
    cities of Durl and Duz.
  </p>
  <p n="28">
    But for me the captain poured into a little jar some heavy yellow wine
    from a small jar which he kept apart among his sacred things. Thick and
    sweet it was, even like honey, yet there was in its heart a mighty, ardent
    fire which had authority over souls of men. It was made, the captain told
    me, with great subtlety by the secret craft of a family of six who lived
    in a hut on the mountains of Hian Min. Once in these mountains, he said,
    he followed the spoor of a bear, and he came suddenly on a man of that
    family who had hunted the same bear, and he was at the end of a narrow way
    with precipice all about him, and his spear was sticking in the bear, and
    the wound was not fatal, and he had no other weapon. And the bear was
    walking towards the man, very slowly because his wound irked him—yet he
    was now very close. And what he captain did he would not say, but every
    year as soon as the snows are hard, and travelling is easy on the Hian
    Min, that man comes down to the market in the plains, and always leaves
    for the captain in the gate of fair Belzoond a vessel of that priceless
    secret wine.
  </p>
  <p n="29">
    And as I sipped the wine and the captain talked, I remembered me of
    stalwart noble things that I had long since resolutely planned, and my
    soul seemed to grow mightier within me and to dominate the whole tide of
    the Yann. It may be that I then slept. Or, if I did not, I do not now
    minutely recollect every detail of that morning’s occupations. Towards
    evening, I awoke and wishing to see Perdóndaris before we left in the
    morning, and being unable to wake the captain, I went ashore alone.
    Certainly Perdóndaris was a powerful city; it was encompassed by a wall of
    great strength and altitude, having in it hollow ways for troops to walk
    in, and battlements along it all the way, and fifteen strong towers on it
    in every mile, and copper plaques low down where men could read them,
    telling in all the languages of those parts of the earth—one language on
    each plaque—the tale of how an army once attacked Perdóndaris and what
    befell that army. Then I entered Perdóndaris and found all the people
    dancing, clad in brilliant silks, and playing on the tambang as they
    danced. For a fearful thunderstorm had terrified them while I slept, and
    the fires of death, they said, had danced over Perdóndaris, and now the
    thunder had gone leaping away large and black and hideous, they said, over
    the distant hills, and had turned round snarling at them, shoving his
    gleaming teeth, and had stamped, as he went, upon the hilltops until they
    rang as though they had been bronze. And often and again they stopped in
    their merry dances and prayed to the God they knew not, saying, <q>O, God
    that we know not, we thank Thee for sending the thunder back to his
    hills.</q> And I went on and came to the market-place, and lying there upon
    the marble pavement I saw the merchant fast asleep and breathing heavily,
    with his face and the palms of his hands towards the sky, and slaves were
    fanning him to keep away the flies. And from the market-place I came to a
    silver temple and then to a palace of onyx, and there were many wonders in
    Perdóndaris, and I would have stayed and seen them all, but as I came to
    the outer wall of the city I suddenly saw in it a huge ivory gate. For a
    while I paused and admired it, then I came nearer and perceived the
    dreadful truth. The gate was carved out of one solid piece!
  </p>
  <p n="30">
    I fled at once through the gateway and down to the ship, and even as I ran
    I thought that I heard far off on the hills behind me the tramp of the
    fearful beast by whom that mass of ivory was shed, who was perhaps even
    then looking for his other tusk. When I was on the ship again I felt
    safer, and I said nothing to the sailors of what I had seen.
  </p>
  <p n="31">
    And now the captain was gradually awakening. Now night was rolling up from
    the East and North, and only the pinnacles of the towers of Perdóndaris
    still took the fallen sunlight. Then I went to the captain and told him
    quietly of the thing I had seen. And he questioned me at once about the
    gate, in a low voice, that the sailors might not know; and I told him how
    the weight of the thing was such that it could not have been brought from
    afar, and the captain knew that it had not been there a year ago. We
    agreed that such a beast could never have been killed by any assault of
    man, and that the gate must have been a fallen tusk, and one fallen near
    and recently. Therefore he decided that it were better to flee at once; so
    he commanded, and the sailors went to the sails, and others raised the
    anchor to the deck, and just as the highest pinnacle of marble lost the
    last rays of the sun we left Perdóndaris, that famous city. And night came
    down and cloaked Perdóndaris and hid it from our eyes, which as things
    have happened will never see it again; for I have heard since that
    something swift and wonderful has suddenly wrecked Perdóndaris in a
    day—towers, walls and people.
  </p>
  <p n="32">
    And the night deepened over the River Yann, a night all white with stars.
    And with the night there rose the helmsman’s song. As soon as he had
    prayed he began to sing to cheer himself all through the lonely night. But
    first he prayed, praying the helmsman’s prayer. And this is what I
    remember of it, rendered into English with a very feeble equivalent of the
    rhythm that seemed so resonant in those tropic nights.
  </p>
  <p n="33">
    To whatever god may hear.
  </p>
  <p n="34">
    Wherever there be sailors whether of river or sea: whether their way be
    dark or whether through storm: whether their peril be of beast or of rock:
    or from enemy lurking on land or pursuing on sea: wherever the tiller is
    cold or the helmsman stiff: wherever sailors sleep or helmsmen watch:
    guard, guide and return us to the old land, that has known us: to the far
    homes that we know.
  </p>
  <p n="35">
    To all the gods that are.
  </p>
  <p n="36">
    To whatever god may hear.
  </p>
  <p n="37">
    So he prayed, and there was silence. And the sailors laid them down to
    rest for the night. The silence deepened, and was only broken by the
    ripples of Yann that lightly touched our prow. Sometimes some monster of
    the river coughed.
  </p>
  <p n="38">
    Silence and ripples, ripples and silence again.
  </p>
  <p n="39">
    And then his loneliness came upon the helmsman, and he began to sing. And
    he sang the market songs of Durl and Duz, and the old dragon-legends of
    Belzoond.
  </p>
  <p n="40">
    Many a song he sang, telling to spacious and exotic Yann the little tales
    and trifles of his city of Durl. And the songs welled up over the black
    jungle and came into the clear cold air above, and the great bands of
    stars that look on Yann began to know the affairs of Durl and Duz, and of
    the shepherds that dwelt in the fields between, and the flocks that they
    had, and the loves that they had loved, and all the little things that
    they had hoped to do. And as I lay wrapped up in skins and blankets,
    listening to those songs, and watching the fantastic shapes of the great
    trees like to black giants stalking through the night, I suddenly fell
    asleep.
  </p>
  <p n="41">
    When I awoke great mists were trailing away from the Yann. And the flow of
    the river was tumbling now tumultuously, and little waves appeared; for
    Yann had scented from afar the ancient crags of Glorm, and knew that their
    ravines lay cool before him wherein he should meet the merry wild Irillion
    rejoicing from fields of snow. So he shook off from him the torpid sleep
    that had come upon him in the hot and scented jungle, and forgot its
    orchids and its butterflies, and swept on turbulent, expectant, strong;
    and soon the snowy peaks of the Hills of Glorm came glittering into view.
    And now the sailors were waking up from sleep. Soon we all ate, and then
    the helmsman laid him down to sleep while a comrade took his place, and
    they all spread over him their choicest furs.
  </p>
  <p n="42">
    And in a while we heard the sound that the Irillion made as she came down
    dancing from the fields of snow.
  </p>
  <p n="43">
    And then we saw the ravine in the Hills of Glorm lying precipitous and
    smooth before us, into which we were carried by the leaps of Yann. And now
    we left the steamy jungle and breathed the mountain air; the sailors stood
    up and took deep breaths of it, and thought of their own far off Acroctian
    hills on which were Durl and Duz—below them in the plains stands fair
    Belzoond.
  </p>
  <p n="44">
    A great shadow brooded between the cliffs of Glorm, but the crags were
    shining above us like gnarled moons, and almost lit the gloom. Louder and
    louder came the Irillion’s song, and the sound of her dancing down from
    the fields of snow. And soon we saw her white and full of mists, and
    wreathed with rainbows delicate and small that she had plucked up near the
    mountain’s summit from some celestial garden of the Sun. Then she went
    away seawards with the huge grey Yann and the ravine widened, and opened
    upon the world, and our rocking ship came through to the light of the day.
  </p>
  <p n="45">
    And all that morning and all the afternoon we passed through the marshes
    of Pondoovery; and Yann widened there, and flowed solemnly and slowly, and
    the captain bade the sailors beat on bells to overcome the dreariness of
    the marshes.
  </p>
  <p n="46">
    At last the Irusian mountains came in sight, nursing the villages of
    Pen-Kai and Blut, and the wandering streets of Mlo, where priests
    propitiate the avalanche with wine and maize. Then night came down over
    the plains of Tlun, and we saw the lights of Cappadarnia. We heard the
    Pathnites beating upon drums as we passed Imaut and Golzunda, then all but
    the helmsman slept. And villages scattered along the banks of the Yann
    heard all that night in the helmsman’s unknown tongue the little songs of
    cities that they knew not.
  </p>
  <p n="47">
    I awoke before dawn with a feeling that I was unhappy before I remembered
    why. Then I recalled that by the evening of the approaching day, according
    to all foreseen probabilities, we should come to Bar-Wul-Yann, and I
    should part from the captain and his sailors. And I had liked the man
    because he had given me of his yellow wine that was set apart among his
    sacred things, and many a story he had told me about his fair Belzoond
    between the Acroctian hills and the Hian Min. And I had liked the ways
    that his sailors had, and the prayers that they prayed at evening side by
    side, grudging not one another their alien gods. And I had a liking too
    for the tender way in which they often spoke of Durl and Duz, for it is
    good that men should love their native cities and the little hills that
    hold those cities up.
  </p>
  <p n="48">
    And I had come to know who would meet them when they returned to their
    homes, and where they thought the meetings would take place, some in a
    valley of the Acroctian hills where the road comes up from Yann, others in
    the gateway of one or another of the three cities, and others by the
    fireside in the home. And I thought of the danger that had menaced us all
    alike outside Perdóndaris, a danger that, as things have happened, was
    very real.
  </p>
  <p n="49">
    And I thought too of the helmsman’s cheery song in the cold and lonely
    night, and how he had held our lives in his careful hands. And as I
    thought of this the helmsman ceased to sing, and I looked up and saw a
    pale light had appeared in the sky, and the lonely night had passed; and
    the dawn widened, and the sailors awoke.
  </p>
  <p n="50">
    And soon we saw the tide of the Sea himself advancing resolute between
    Yann’s borders, and Yann sprang lithely at him and they struggled awhile;
    then Yann and all that was his were pushed back northward, so that the
    sailors had to hoist the sails and, the wind being favorable, we still
    held onwards.
  </p>
  <p n="51">
    And we passed Gondara and Narl and Haz. And we saw memorable, holy Golnuz,
    and heard the pilgrims praying.
  </p>
  <p n="52">
    When we awoke after the midday rest we were coming near to Nen, the last
    of the cities on the River Yann. And the jungle was all about us once
    again, and about Nen; but the great Mloon ranges stood up over all things,
    and watched the city from beyond the jungle.
  </p>
  <p n="53">
    Here we anchored, and the captain and I went up into the city and found
    that the Wanderers had come into Nen.
  </p>
  <p n="54">
    And the Wanderers were a weird, dark, tribe, that once in every seven
    years came down from the peaks of Mloon, having crossed by a pass that is
    known to them from some fantastic land that lies beyond. And the people of
    Nen were all outside their houses, and all stood wondering at their own
    streets. For the men and women of the Wanderers had crowded all the ways,
    and every one was doing some strange thing. Some danced astounding dances
    that they had learned from the desert wind, rapidly curving and swirling
    till the eye could follow no longer. Others played upon instruments
    beautiful wailing tunes that were full of horror, which souls had taught
    them lost by night in the desert, that strange far desert from which the
    Wanderers came.
  </p>
  <p n="55">
    None of their instruments were such as were known in Nen nor in any part
    of the region of the Yann; even the horns out of which some were made were
    of beasts that none had seen along the river, for they were barbed at the
    tips. And they sang, in the language of none, songs that seemed to be akin
    to the mysteries of night and to the unreasoned fear that haunts dark
    places.
  </p>
  <p n="56">
    Bitterly all the dogs of Nen distrusted them. And the Wanderers told one
    another fearful tales, for though no one in Nen knew ought of their
    language yet they could see the fear on the listeners’ faces, and as the
    tale wound on the whites of their eyes showed vividly in terror as the
    eyes of some little beast whom the hawk has seized. Then the teller of the
    tale would smile and stop, and another would tell his story, and the
    teller of the first tale’s lips would chatter with fear. And if some
    deadly snake chanced to appear the Wanderers would greet him as a brother,
    and the snake would seem to give his greetings to them before he passed on
    again. Once that most fierce and lethal of tropic snakes, the giant
    lythra, came out of the jungle and all down the street, the central street
    of Nen, and none of the Wanderers moved away from him, but they all played
    sonorously on drums, as though he had been a person of much honour; and
    the snake moved through the midst of them and smote none.
  </p>
  <p n="57">
    Even the Wanderers’ children could do strange things, for if any one of
    them met with a child of Nen the two would stare at each other in silence
    with large grave eyes; then the Wanderers’ child would slowly draw from
    his turban a live fish or snake. And the children of Nen could do nothing
    of that kind at all.
  </p>
  <p n="58">
    Much I should have wished to stay and hear the hymn with which they greet
    the night, that is answered by the wolves on the heights of Mloon, but it
    was now time to raise the anchor again that the captain might return from
    Bar-Wul-Yann upon the landward tide. So we went on board and continued
    down the Yann. And the captain and I spoke little, for we were thinking of
    our parting, which should be for long, and we watched instead the
    splendour of the westerning sun. For the sun was a ruddy gold, but a faint
    mist cloaked the jungle, lying low, and into it poured the smoke of the
    little jungle cities, and the smoke of them met together in the mist and
    joined into one haze, which became purple, and was lit by the sun, as the
    thoughts of men become hallowed by some great and sacred thing. Some times
    one column from a lonely house would rise up higher than the cities’
    smoke, and gleam by itself in the sun.
  </p>
  <p n="59">
    And now as the sun’s last rays were nearly level, we saw the sight that I
    had come to see, for from two mountains that stood on either shore two
    cliffs of pink marble came out into the river, all glowing in the light of
    the low sun, and they were quite smooth and of mountainous altitude, and
    they nearly met, and Yann went tumbling between them and found the sea.
  </p>
  <p n="60">
    And this was Bar-Wul-Yann, the Gate of Yann, and in the distance through
    that barrier’s gap I saw the azure indescribable sea, where little
    fishing-boats went gleaming by.
  </p>
  <p n="61">
    And the sun set, and the brief twilight came, and the exultation of the
    glory of Bar-Wul-Yann was gone, yet still the pink cliffs glowed, the
    fairest marvel that the eye beheld—and this in a land of wonders. And
    soon the twilight gave place to the coming out of stars, and the colours
    of Bar-Wul-Yann went dwindling away. And the sight of those cliffs was to
    me as some chord of music that a master’s hand had launched from the
    violin, and which carries to Heaven or Faëry the tremulous spirits of men.
  </p>
  <p n="62">
    And now by the shore they anchored and went no further, for they were
    sailors of the river and not of the sea, and knew the Yann but not the
    tides beyond.
  </p>
  <p n="63">
    And the time was come when the captain and I must part, he to go back to
    his fair Belzoond in sight of the distant peaks of the Hian Min, and I to
    find my way by strange means back to those hazy fields that all poets
    know, wherein stand small mysterious cottages through whose windows,
    looking westwards, you may see the fields of men, and looking eastwards
    see glittering elfin mountains, tipped with snow, going range on range
    into the region of Myth, and beyond it into the kingdom of Fantasy, which
    pertain to the Lands of Dream. Long we regarded one another, knowing that
    we should meet no more, for my fancy is weakening as the years slip by,
    and I go ever more seldom into the Lands of Dream. Then we clasped hands,
    uncouthly on his part, for it is not the method of greeting in his
    country, and he commended my soul to the care of his own gods, to his
    little lesser gods, the humble ones, to the gods that bless Belzoond.
  </p>
</div>
