<div>
  <head>THE LOOT OF BOMBASHARNA</head>
  <p n="1">
    Things had grown too hot for Shard, captain of pirates, on all the
    seas that he knew. The ports of Spain were closed to him; they knew
    him in San Domingo; men winked in Syracuse when he went by; the two
    Kings of the Sicilies never smiled within an hour of speaking of him;
    there were huge rewards for his head in every capital city, with
    pictures of it for identification—<hi>and all the pictures were
    unflattering</hi>. Therefore Captain Shard decided that the time had come
    to tell his men the secret.
  </p>
  <p n="2">
    Riding off Teneriffe one night, he called them all together. He
    generously admitted that there were things in the past that might
    require explanation: the crowns that the Princes of Aragon had sent to
    their nephews the Kings of the two Americas had certainly never
    reached their Most Sacred Majesties. Where, men might ask, were the
    eyes of Captain Stobbud? Who had been burning towns on the Patagonian
    seaboard? Why should such a ship as theirs choose pearls for cargo?
    Why so much blood on the decks and so many guns? And where was the
    <hi>Nancy</hi>, the <hi>Lark</hi>, or the <hi>Margaret Belle</hi>? Such questions as these,
    he urged, might be asked by the inquisitive, and if counsel for the
    defence should happen to be a fool, and unacquainted with the ways of
    the sea, they might become involved in troublesome legal formulae. And
    Bloody Bill, as they rudely called Mr. Gagg, a member of the crew,
    looked up at the sky, and said that it was a windy night and looked
    like hanging. And some of those present thoughtfully stroked their
    necks while Captain Shard unfolded to them his plan. He said the time
    was come to quit the <hi>Desperate Lark</hi>, for she was too well known to
    the navies of four kingdoms, and a fifth was getting to know her, and
    others had suspicions. (More cutters than even Captain Shard suspected
    were already looking for her jolly black flag with its neat
    skull-and-crossbones in yellow.) There was a little archipelago that
    he knew of on the wrong side of the Sargasso Sea; there were about
    thirty islands there, bare, ordinary islands, but one of them floated.
    He had noticed it years ago, and had gone ashore and never told a
    soul, but had quietly anchored it with the anchor of his ship to the
    bottom of the sea, which just there was profoundly deep, and had made
    the thing the secret of his life, determining to marry and settle down
    there if it ever became impossible to earn his livelihood in the usual
    way at sea. When first he saw it, it was drifting slowly, with the
    wind in the tops of the trees; but if the cable had not rusted away,
    it should be still where he left it, and they would make a rudder and
    hollow out cabins below, and at night they would hoist sails to the
    trunks of the trees and sail wherever they liked.
  </p>
  <p n="3">
    And all the pirates cheered, for they wanted to set their feet on land
    again somewhere where the hangman would not come and jerk them off it
    at once; and bold men though they were, it was a strain seeing so many
    lights coming their way at night. Even then...! But it swerved away
    again and was lost in the mist.
  </p>
  <p n="4">
    And Captain Shard said that they would need to get provisions first,
    and he, for one, intended to marry before he settled down; and so they
    should have one more fight before they left the ship, and sack the
    sea-coast city of Bombasharna and take from it provisions for several
    years, while he himself would marry the Queen of the South. And again
    the pirates cheered, for often they had seen seacoast Bombasharna, and
    had always envied its opulence from the sea.
  </p>
  <p n="5">
    So they set all sail, and often altered their course, and dodged and
    fled from strange lights till dawn appeared, and all day long fled
    southwards. And by evening they saw the silver spires of slender
    Bombasharna, a city that was the glory of the coast. And in the midst
    of it, far away though they were, they saw the palace of the Queen of
    the South; and it was so full of windows all looking toward the sea,
    and they were so full of light, both from the sunset that was fading
    upon the water and from candles that maids were lighting one by one,
    that it looked far off like a pearl, shimmering still in its haliotis
    shell, still wet from the sea.
  </p>
  <p n="6">
    So Captain Shard and his pirates saw it, at evening over the water,
    and thought of rumours that said that Bombasharna was the loveliest
    city of the coasts of the world, and that its palace was lovelier even
    than Bombasharna; but for the Queen of the South rumour had no
    comparison. Then night came down and hid the silver spires, and Shard
    slipped on through the gathering darkness until by midnight the
    piratic ship lay under the seaward battlements.
  </p>
  <p n="7">
    And at the hour when sick men mostly die, and sentries on lonely
    ramparts stand to arms, exactly half-an-hour before dawn, Shard, with
    two rowing boats and half his crew, with craftily muffled oars, landed
    below the battlements. They were through the gateway of the palace
    itself before the alarm was sounded, and as soon as they heard the
    alarm Shard’s gunners at sea opened upon the town, and before the
    sleepy soldiery of Bombasharna knew whether the danger was from the
    land or the sea, Shard had successfully captured the Queen of the
    South. They would have looted all day that silver sea-coast city, but
    there appeared with dawn suspicious topsails just along the horizon.
    Therefore the captain with his Queen went down to the shore at once
    and hastily re-embarked and sailed away with what loot they had
    hurriedly got, and with fewer men, for they had to fight a good deal to
    get back to the boat. They cursed all day the interference of those
    ominous ships which steadily grew nearer. There were six ships at
    first, and that night they slipped away from all but two; but all the
    next day those two were still in sight, and each of them had more guns
    than the <hi>Desperate Lark</hi>. All the next night Shard dodged about the
    sea, but the two ships separated and one kept him in sight, and the
    next morning it was alone with Shard on the sea, and his archipelago
    was just in sight, the secret of his life.
  </p>
  <p n="8">
    And Shard saw he must fight, and a bad fight it was, and yet it suited
    Shard’s purpose, for he had more merry men when the fight began than
    he needed for his island. And they got it over before any other ship
    came up; and Shard put all adverse evidence out of the way, and came
    that night to the islands near the Sargasso Sea.
  </p>
  <p n="9">
    Long before it was light the survivors of the crew were peering at the
    sea, and when dawn came there was the island, no bigger than two
    ships, straining hard at its anchor, with the wind in the tops of the
    trees.
  </p>
  <p n="10">
    And then they landed and dug cabins below and raised the anchor out of
    the deep sea, and soon they made the island what they called
    shipshape. But the <hi>Desperate Lark</hi> they sent away empty under full
    sail to sea, where more nations than Shard suspected were watching for
    her, and where she was presently captured by an admiral of Spain, who,
    when he found none of that famous crew on board to hang by the neck
    from the yard-arm, grew ill through disappointment.
  </p>
  <p n="11">
    And Shard on his island offered the Queen of the South the choicest of
    the old wines of Provence, and for adornment gave her Indian jewels
    looted from galleons with treasure for Madrid, and spread a table
    where she dined in the sun, while in some cabin below he bade the
    least coarse of his mariners sing; yet always she was morose and moody
    towards him, and often at evening he was heard to say that he wished
    he knew more about the ways of Queens. So they lived for years, the
    pirates mostly gambling and drinking below, Captain Shard trying to
    please the Queen of the South, and she never wholly forgetting
    Bombasharna. When they needed new provisions they hoisted sails on the
    trees, and as long as no ship came in sight they scudded before the
    wind, with the water rippling over the beach of the island; but as
    soon as they sighted a ship the sails came down, and they became an
    ordinary uncharted rock.
  </p>
  <p n="12">
    They mostly moved by night; sometimes they hovered off sea-coast towns
    as of old, sometimes they boldly entered river-mouths, and even
    attached themselves for a while to the mainland, whence they would
    plunder the neighbourhood and escape again to sea. And if a ship was
    wrecked on their island of a night they said it was all to the good.
    They grew very crafty in seamanship, and cunning in what they did, for
    they knew that any news of the <hi>Desperate Lark</hi>’s old crew would bring
    hangmen from the interior running down to every port.
  </p>
  <p n="13">
    And no one is known to have found them out or to have annexed their
    island; but a rumour arose and passed from port to port and every
    place where sailors meet together, and even survives to this day, of a
    dangerous uncharted rock anywhere between Plymouth and the Horn, which
    would suddenly rise in the safest track of ships, and upon which
    vessels were supposed to have been wrecked, leaving, strangely enough,
    no evidence of their doom. There was a little speculation about it at
    first, till it was silenced by the chance remark of a man old with
    wandering: <q>It is one of the mysteries that haunt the sea.</q>
  </p>
  <p n="14">
    And almost Captain Shard and the Queen of the South lived happily ever
    after, though still at evening those on watch in the trees would see
    their captain sit with a puzzled air or hear him muttering now and again
    in a discontented way: <q>I wish I knew more about the ways of Queens.</q>
  </p>
</div>
