<div>
  <head>PROBABLE ADVENTURE OF THE THREE LITERARY MEN</head>
  <p n="1">
    When the nomads came to El Lola they had no more songs, and the
    question of stealing the golden box arose in all its magnitude. On the
    one hand, many had sought the golden box, the receptacle (as the
    Aethiopians know) of poems of fabulous value; and their doom is still
    the common talk of Arabia. On the other hand, it was lonely to sit
    around the camp-fire by night with no new songs.
  </p>
  <p n="2">
    It was the tribe of Heth that discussed these things one evening upon
    the plains below the peak of Mluna. Their native land was the track
    across the world of immemorial wanderers; and there was trouble among
    the elders of the nomads because there were no new songs; while,
    untouched by human trouble, untouched as yet by the night that was
    hiding the plains away, the peak of Mluna, calm in the after-glow,
    looked on the Dubious Land. And it was there on the plain upon the
    known side of Mluna, just as the evening star came mouse-like into
    view and the flames of the camp-fire lifted their lonely plumes
    uncheered by any song, that that rash scheme was hastily planned by
    the nomads which the world has named The Quest of the Golden Box.
  </p>
  <p n="3">
    No measure of wiser precaution could the elders of the nomads have
    taken than to choose for their thief that very Slith, that identical
    thief that (even as I write) in how many school-rooms governesses
    teach stole a march on the King of Westalia. Yet the weight of the box
    was such that others had to accompany him, and Sippy and Slorg were no
    more agile thieves than may be found today among vendors of the
    antique.
  </p>
  <p n="4">
    So over the shoulder of Mluna these three climbed next day and slept
    as well as they might among its snows rather than risk a night in the
    woods of the Dubious Land. And the morning came up radiant and the
    birds were full of song, but the forest underneath and the waste
    beyond it and the bare and ominous crags all wore the appearance of an
    unuttered threat.
  </p>
  <p n="5">
    Though Slith had an experience of twenty years of theft, yet he said
    little; only if one of the others made a stone roll with his foot, or,
    later on in the forest, if one of them stepped on a twig, he whispered
    sharply to them always the same words: <q>That is not business.</q> He knew
    that he could not make them better thieves during a two days’ journey,
    and whatever doubts he had he interfered no further.
  </p>
  <p n="6">
    From the shoulder of Mluna they dropped into the clouds, and from the
    clouds to the forest, to whose native beasts, as well the three
    thieves knew, all flesh was meat, whether it were the flesh of fish or
    man. There the thieves drew idolatrously from their pockets each one a
    separate god and prayed for protection in the unfortunate wood, and
    hoped therefrom for a threefold chance of escape, since if anything
    should eat one of them it were certain to eat them all, and they
    confided that the corollary might be true and all should escape if one
    did. Whether one of these gods was propitious and awake, or whether
    all of the three, or whether it was chance that brought them through
    the forest unmouthed by detestable beasts, none knoweth; but certainly
    neither the emissaries of the god that most they feared, nor the wrath
    of the topical god of that ominous place, brought their doom to the
    three adventurers there or then. And so it was that they came to
    Rumbly Heath, in the heart of the Dubious Land, whose stormy hillocks
    were the ground-swell and the after-wash of the earthquake lulled for
    a while. Something so huge that it seemed unfair to man that it should
    move so softly stalked splendidly by them, and only so barely did they
    escape its notice that one word rang and echoed through their three
    imaginations—<q>If—if—if.</q> And when this danger was at last gone by
    they moved cautiously on again and presently saw the little harmless
    mipt, half fairy and half gnome, giving shrill, contented squeaks on
    the edge of the world. And they edged away unseen, for they said that
    the inquisitiveness of the mipt had become fabulous, and that,
    harmless as he was, he had a bad way with secrets; yet they probably
    loathed the way that he nuzzles dead white bones, and would not admit
    their loathing; for it does not become adventurers to care who eats
    their bones. Be this as it may, they edged away from the mipt, and
    came almost at once to the wizened tree, the goal-post of their
    adventure, and knew that beside them was the crack in the world and
    the bridge from Bad to Worse, and that underneath them stood the rocky
    house of Owner of the Box.
  </p>
  <p n="7">
    This was their simple plan: to slip into the corridor in the upper
    cliff; to run softly down it (of course with naked feet) under the
    warning to travellers that is graven upon stone, which interpreters
    take to be <q>It Is Better Not</q>; not to touch the berries that are there
    for a purpose, on the right side going down; and so to come to the
    guardian on his pedestal who had slept for a thousand years and should
    be sleeping still; and go in through the open window. One man was to
    wait outside by the crack in the World until the others came out with
    the golden box, and, should they cry for help, he was to threaten at
    once to unfasten the iron clamp that kept the crack together. When the
    box was secured they were to travel all night and all the following
    day, until the cloud-banks that wrapped the slopes of Mluna were well
    between them and Owner of the Box.
  </p>
  <p n="8">
    The door in the cliff was open. They passed without a murmur down the
    cold steps, Slith leading them all the way. A glance of longing, no
    more, each gave to the beautiful berries. The guardian upon his
    pedestal was still asleep. Slorg climbed by a ladder, that Slith knew
    where to find, to the iron clamp across the crack in the World, and
    waited beside it with a chisel in his hand, listening closely for
    anything untoward, while his friends slipped into the house; and no
    sound came. And presently Slith and Sippy found the golden box:
    everything seemed happening as they had planned, it only remained to
    see if it was the right one and to escape with it from that dreadful
    place. Under the shelter of the pedestal, so near to the guardian that
    they could feel his warmth, which paradoxically had the effect of
    chilling the blood of the boldest of them, they smashed the emerald
    hasp and opened the golden box; and there they read by the light of
    ingenious sparks which Slith knew how to contrive, and even this poor
    light they hid with their bodies. What was their joy, even at that
    perilous moment, as they lurked between the guardian and the abyss, to
    find that the box contained fifteen peerless odes in the alcaic form,
    five sonnets that were by far the most beautiful in the world, nine
    ballads in the manner of Provence that had no equal in the treasuries
    of man, a poem addressed to a moth in twenty-eight perfect stanzas, a
    piece of blank verse of over a hundred lines on a level not yet known
    to have been attained by man, as well as fifteen lyrics on which no
    merchant would dare to set a price. They would have read them again,
    for they gave happy tears to a man and memories of dear things done in
    infancy, and brought sweet voices from far sepulchres; but Slith
    pointed imperiously to the way by which they had come, and
    extinguished the light; and Slorg and Sippy sighed, then took the box.
  </p>
  <p n="9">
    The guardian still slept the sleep that survived a thousand years.
  </p>
  <p n="10">
    As they came away they saw that indulgent chair close by the edge of
    the World in which Owner of the Box had lately sat reading
    selfishly and alone the most beautiful songs and verses that poet ever
    dreamed.
  </p>
  <p n="11">
    They came in silence to the foot of the stairs; and then it befell
    that as they drew near safely, in the night’s most secret hour, some
    hand in an upper chamber lit a shocking light, lit it and made no
    sound.
  </p>
  <p n="12">
    For a moment it might have been an ordinary light, fatal as even that
    could very well be at such a moment as this; but when it began to
    follow them like an eye and to grow redder and redder as it watched
    them, then even optimism despaired.
  </p>
  <p n="13">
    And Sippy very unwisely attempted flight, and Slorg even as unwisely
    tried to hide; but Slith, knowing well why that light was lit in that
    secret upper chamber and <hi>who</hi> it was that lit it, leaped over the edge
    of the World and is falling from us still through the unreverberate
    blackness of the abyss.
  </p>
</div>
