<div>
  <head>THE HOUSE OF THE SPHINX</head>
  <p n="1">
    When I came to the House of the Sphinx it was already dark. They made
    me eagerly welcome. And I, in spite of the deed, was glad of any
    shelter from that ominous wood. I saw at once that there had been a
    deed, although a cloak did all that a cloak may do to conceal it. The
    mere uneasiness of the welcome made me suspect that cloak.
  </p>
  <p n="2">
    The Sphinx was moody and silent. I had not come to pry into the
    secrets of Eternity nor to investigate the Sphinx’s private life, and
    so had little to say and few questions to ask; but to whatever I did
    say she remained morosely indifferent. It was clear that either she
    suspected me of being in search of the secrets of one of her gods, or
    of being boldly inquisitive about her traffic with Time, or else she
    was darkly absorbed with brooding upon the deed.
  </p>
  <p n="3">
    I saw soon enough that there was another than me to welcome; I saw it
    from the hurried way that they glanced from the door to the deed and
    back to the door again. And it was clear that the welcome was to be a
    bolted door. But such bolts, and such a door! Rust and decay and
    fungus had been there far too long, and it was not a barrier any
    longer that would keep out even a determined wolf. And it seemed to be
    something worse than a wolf that they feared.
  </p>
  <p n="4">
    A little later on I gathered from what they said that some imperious
    and ghastly thing was looking for the Sphinx, and that something that
    had happened had made its arrival certain. It appeared that they had
    slapped the Sphinx to vex her out of her apathy in order that she
    should pray to one of her gods, whom she had littered in the house of
    Time; but her moody silence was invincible, and her apathy Oriental,
    ever since the deed had happened. And when they found that they could
    not make her pray, there was nothing for them to do but to pay little
    useless attentions to the rusty lock of the door, and to look at the
    deed and wonder, and even pretend to hope, and to say that after all
    it might not bring that destined thing from the forest, which no one
    named.
  </p>
  <p n="5">
    It may be said I had chosen a gruesome house, but not if I had
    described the forest from which I came, and I was in need of any spot
    wherein I could rest my mind from the thought of it.
  </p>
  <p n="6">
    I wondered very much what thing would come from the forest on account
    of the deed; and having seen that forest—as you, gentle reader, have
    not—I had the advantage of knowing that anything might come. It was
    useless to ask the Sphinx—she seldom reveals things, like her
    paramour Time (the gods take after her), and while this mood was on
    her, rebuff was certain. So I quietly began to oil the lock of the
    door. And as soon as they saw this simple act I won their confidence.
    It was not that my work was of any use—it should have been done long
    before; but they saw that my interest was given for the moment to the
    thing that they thought vital. They clustered round me then. They
    asked me what I thought of the door, and whether I had seen better,
    and whether I had seen worse; and I told them about all the doors I
    knew, and said that the doors of the baptistry in Florence were better
    doors, and the doors made by a certain firm of builders in London were
    worse. And then I asked them what it was that was coming after the
    Sphinx because of the deed. And at first they would not say, and I
    stopped oiling the door; and then they said that it was the
    arch-inquisitor of the forest, who is investigator and avenger of all
    silverstrian things; and from all that they said about him it seemed to me
    that this person was quite white, and was a kind of madness that would
    settle down quite blankly upon a place, a kind of mist in which reason
    could not live; and it was the fear of this that made them fumble
    nervously at the lock of that rotten door; but with the Sphinx it was
    not so much fear as sheer prophecy.
  </p>
  <p n="7">
    The hope that they tried to hope was well enough in its way, but I did
    not share it; it was clear that the thing that they feared was the
    corollary of the deed—one saw that more by the resignation upon the
    face of the Sphinx than by their sorry anxiety for the door.
  </p>
  <p n="8">
    The wind soughed, and the great tapers flared, and their obvious fear
    and the silence of the Sphinx grew more than ever a part of the
    atmosphere, and bats went restlessly through the gloom of the wind
    that beat the tapers low.
  </p>
  <p n="9">
    Then a few things screamed far off, then a little nearer, and
    something was coming towards us, laughing hideously. I hastily gave a
    prod to the door that they guarded; my finger sank right into the
    mouldering wood—there was not a chance of holding it. I had not
    leisure to observe their fright; I thought of the back-door, for the
    forest was better than this; only the Sphinx was absolutely calm, her
    prophecy was made and she seemed to have seen her doom, so that no new
    thing could perturb her.
  </p>
  <p n="10">
    But by mouldering rungs of ladders as old as Man, by slippery edges of
    the dreaded abyss, with an ominous dizziness about my heart and a
    feeling of horror in the soles of my feet, I clambered from tower to
    tower till I found the door that I sought; and it opened on to one of
    the upper branches of a huge and sombre pine, down which I climbed on
    to the floor of the forest. And I was glad to be back again in the
    forest from which I had fled.
  </p>
  <p n="11">
    And the Sphinx in her menaced house—I know not how she fared—whether
    she gazes for ever, disconsolate, at the deed, remembering only in her
    smitten mind, at which the little boys now leer, that she once knew
    well those things at which man stands aghast; or whether in the end
    she crept away, and clambering horribly from abyss to abyss, came at
    last to higher things, and is wise and eternal still. For who knows of
    madness whether it is divine or whether it be of the pit?
  </p>
</div>
