<div>
  <head>HOW NUTH WOULD HAVE PRACTISED HIS ART UPON THE GNOLES</head>
  <p n="1">
    Despite the advertisements of rival firms, it is probable that every
    tradesman knows that nobody in business at the present time has a
    position equal to that of Mr. Nuth. To those outside the magic circle
    of business, his name is scarcely known; he does not need to
    advertise, he is consummate. He is superior even to modern
    competition, and, whatever claims they boast, his rivals know it. His
    terms are moderate, so much cash down when the goods are
    delivered, so much in blackmail afterwards. He consults your
    convenience. His skill may be counted upon; I have seen a shadow on a
    windy night move more noisily than Nuth, for Nuth is a burglar by
    trade. Men have been known to stay in country houses and to send a
    dealer afterwards to bargain for a piece of tapestry that they saw
    there—some article of furniture, some picture. This is bad taste: but
    those whose culture is more elegant invariably send Nuth a night or
    two after their visit. He has a way with tapestry; you would scarcely
    notice that the edges had been cut. And often when I see some huge,
    new house full of old furniture and portraits from other ages, I say
    to myself, <q>These mouldering chairs, these full-length ancestors and
    carved mahogany are the produce of the incomparable Nuth.</q>
  </p>
  <p n="2">
    It may be urged against my use of the word incomparable that in the
    burglary business the name of Slith stands paramount and alone; and of
    this I am not ignorant; but Slith is a classic, and lived long ago,
    and knew nothing at all of modern competition; besides which the
    surprising nature of his doom has possibly cast a glamour upon Slith
    that exaggerates in our eyes his undoubted merits.
  </p>
  <p n="3">
    It must not be thought that I am a friend of Nuth’s; on the contrary
    such politics as I have are on the side of Property; and he needs no
    words from me, for his position is almost unique in trade, being among
    the very few that do not need to advertise.
  </p>
  <p n="4">
    At the time that my story begins Nuth lived in a roomy house in
    Belgrave Square: in his inimitable way he had made friends with the
    caretaker. The place suited Nuth, and, whenever anyone came to inspect
    it before purchase, the caretaker used to praise the house in the
    words that Nuth had suggested. <q>If it wasn’t for the drains,</q> she
    would say, <q>it’s the finest house in London,</q> and when they pounced on
    this remark and asked questions about the drains, she would answer
    them that the drains also were good, but not so good as the house.
    They did not see Nuth when they went over the rooms, but Nuth was
    there.
  </p>
  <p n="5">
    Here in a neat black dress on one spring morning came an old woman
    whose bonnet was lined with red, asking for Mr. Nuth; and with her
    came her large and awkward son. Mrs. Eggins, the caretaker, glanced up
    the street, and then she let them in, and left them to wait in the
    drawing-room amongst furniture all mysterious with sheets. For a long
    while they waited, and then there was a smell of pipe-tobacco, and
    there was Nuth standing quite close to them.
  </p>
  <p n="6">
    <q>Lord,</q> said the old woman whose bonnet was lined with red, <q>you did
    make me start.</q> And then she saw by his eyes that that was not the way
    to speak to Mr. Nuth.
  </p>
  <p n="7">
    And at last Nuth spoke, and very nervously the old woman explained
    that her son was a likely lad, and had been in business already but
    wanted to better himself, and she wanted Mr. Nuth to teach him a
    livelihood.
  </p>
  <p n="8">
    First of all Nuth wanted to see a business reference, and when he was
    shown one from a jeweller with whom he happened to be hand-in-glove
    the upshot of it was that he agreed to take young Tonker (for this was
    the surname of the likely lad) and to make him his apprentice. And the
    old woman whose bonnet was lined with red went back to her little
    cottage in the country, and every evening said to her old man,
    <q>Tonker, we must fasten the shutters of a night-time, for Tommy’s a
    burglar now.</q>
  </p>
  <p n="9">
    The details of the likely lad’s apprenticeship I do not propose to
    give; for those that are in the business know those details already,
    and those that are in other businesses care only for their own, while
    men of leisure who have no trade at all would fail to appreciate the
    gradual degrees by which Tommy Tonker came first to cross bare boards,
    covered with little obstacles in the dark, without making any sound,
    and then to go silently up creaky stairs, and then to open doors, and
    lastly to climb.
  </p>
  <p n="10">
    Let it suffice that the business prospered greatly, while glowing
    reports of Tommy Tonker’s progress were sent from time to time to the
    old woman whose bonnet was lined with red in the labourious
    handwriting of Nuth. Nuth had given up lessons in writing very early,
    for he seemed to have some prejudice against forgery, and therefore
    considered writing a waste of time. And then there came the
    transaction with Lord Castlenorman at his Surrey residence. Nuth
    selected a Saturday night, for it chanced that Saturday was observed
    as Sabbath in the family of Lord Castlenorman, and by eleven o’clock
    the whole house was quiet. Five minutes before midnight Tommy Tonker,
    instructed by Mr. Nuth, who waited outside, came away with one
    pocketful of rings and shirt-studs. It was quite a light pocketful,
    but the jewellers in Paris could not match it without sending
    specially to Africa, so that Lord Castlenorman had to borrow bone
    shirt-studs.
  </p>
  <p n="11">
    Not even rumour whispered the name of Nuth. Were I to say that this
    turned his head, there are those to whom the assertion would give
    pain, for his associates hold that his astute judgment was unaffected
    by circumstance. I will say, therefore, that it spurred his genius to
    plan what no burglar had ever planned before. It was nothing less than
    to burgle the house of the gnoles. And this that abstemious man
    unfolded to Tonker over a cup of tea. Had Tonker not been nearly
    insane with pride over their recent transaction, and had he not been
    blinded by a veneration for Nuth, he would have—but I cry over spilt
    milk. He expostulated respectfully; he said he would rather not go; he
    said it was not fair; he allowed himself to argue; and in the end, one
    windy October morning with a menace in the air found him and Nuth
    drawing near to the dreadful wood.
  </p>
  <p n="12">
    Nuth, by weighing little emeralds against pieces of common rock, had
    ascertained the probable weight of those house-ornaments that the
    gnoles are believed to possess in the narrow, lofty house wherein they
    have dwelt from of old. They decided to steal two emeralds and to
    carry them between them on a cloak; but if they should be too heavy
    one must be dropped at once. Nuth warned young Tonker against greed,
    and explained that the emeralds were worth less than cheese until they
    were safe away from the dreadful wood.
  </p>
  <p n="13">
    Everything had been planned, and they walked now in silence.
  </p>
  <p n="14">
    No track led up to the sinister gloom of the trees, either of men or
    cattle; not even a poacher had been there snaring elves for over a
    hundred years. You did not trespass twice in the dells of the gnoles.
    And, apart from the things that were done there, the trees themselves
    were a warning, and did not wear the wholesome look of those that we
    plant ourselves.
  </p>
  <p n="15">
    The nearest village was some miles away with the backs of all its
    houses turned to the wood, and without one window at all facing in
    that direction. They did not speak of it there, and elsewhere it is
    unheard of.
  </p>
  <p n="16">
    Into this wood stepped Nuth and Tommy Tonker. They had no firearms.
    Tonker had asked for a pistol, but Nuth replied that the sound of a
    shot <q>would bring everything down on us,</q> and no more was said about
    it.
  </p>
  <p n="17">
    Into the wood they went all day, deeper and deeper. They saw the
    skeleton of some early Georgian poacher nailed to a door in an oak
    tree; sometimes they saw a fairy scuttle away from them; once Tonker
    stepped heavily on a hard, dry stick, after which they both lay still
    for twenty minutes. And the sunset flared full of omens through the
    tree trunks, and night fell, and they came by fitful starlight, as
    Nuth had foreseen, to that lean, high house where the gnoles so
    secretly dwelt.
  </p>
  <p n="18">
    All was so silent by that unvalued house that the faded courage of
    Tonker flickered up, but to Nuth’s experienced sense it seemed too
    silent; and all the while there was that look in the sky that was
    worse than a spoken doom, so that Nuth, as is often the case when men
    are in doubt, had leisure to fear the worst. Nevertheless he did not
    abandon the business, but sent the likely lad with the instruments of
    his trade by means of the ladder to the old green casement. And the
    moment that Tonker touched the withered boards, the silence that,
    though ominous, was earthly, became unearthly like the touch of a
    ghoul. And Tonker heard his breath offending against that silence, and
    his heart was like mad drums in a night attack, and a string of one of
    his sandals went tap on a rung of a ladder, and the leaves of the
    forest were mute, and the breeze of the night was still; and Tonker
    prayed that a mouse or a mole might make any noise at all, but not a
    creature stirred, even Nuth was still. And then and there, while yet
    he was undiscovered, the likely lad made up his mind, as he should
    have done long before, to leave those colossal emeralds where they
    were and have nothing further to do with the lean, high house of the
    gnoles, but to quit this sinister wood in the nick of time and retire
    from business at once and buy a place in the country. Then he
    descended softly and beckoned to Nuth. But the gnoles had watched him
    through knavish holes that they bore in trunks of the trees, and the
    unearthly silence gave way, as it were with a grace, to the rapid
    screams of Tonker as they picked him up from behind—screams that came
    faster and faster until they were incoherent. And where they took him
    it is not good to ask, and what they did with him I shall not say.
  </p>
  <p n="19">
    Nuth looked on for a while from the corner of the house with a mild
    surprise on his face as he rubbed his chin, for the trick of the holes
    in the trees was new to him; then he stole nimbly away through the
    dreadful wood.
  </p>
  <p n="20">
    <q>And did they catch Nuth?</q> you ask me, gentle reader.
  </p>
  <p n="21">
    <q>Oh, no, my child</q> (for such a question is childish). <q>Nobody ever
    catches Nuth.</q>
  </p>
</div>
