<div>
  <head>The Bad Old Woman in Black</head>
  <p n="1">
    The bad old woman in black ran down the street of the ox-butchers.
  </p>
  <p n="2">
    Windows at once were opened high up in those crazy gables; heads were
    thrust out: it was she. Then there arose the counsel of anxious
    voices, calling sideways from window to window or across to opposite
    houses. Why was she there with her sequins and bugles and old black
    gown? Why had she left her dreaded house? On what fell errand she
    hasted?
  </p>
  <p n="3">
    They watched her lean, lithe figure, and the wind in that old black
    dress, and soon she was gone from the cobbled street and under the
    town’s high gateway. She turned at once to her right and was hid from
    the view of the houses. Then they all ran down to their doors, and
    small groups formed on the pavement; there they took counsel together,
    the eldest speaking first. Of what they had seen they said nothing,
    for there was no doubt it was she; it was of the future they spoke,
    and the future only.
  </p>
  <p n="4">
    In what notorious thing would her errand end? What gains had tempted
    her out from her fearful home? What brilliant but sinful scheme had
    her genius planned? Above all, what future evil did this portend? Thus
    at first it was only questions. And then the old grey-beards spoke,
    each one to a little group; they had seen her out before, had known
    her when she was younger, and had noted the evil things that had
    followed her goings: the small groups listened well to their low and
    earnest voices. No one asked questions now or guessed at her infamous
    errand, but listened only to the wise old men who knew the things that
    had been, and who told the younger men of the dooms that had come
    before.
  </p>
  <p n="5">
    Nobody knew how many times she had left her dreaded house; but the
    oldest recounted all the times that they knew, and the way she had
    gone each time, and the doom that had followed her going; and two
    could remember the earthquake that there was in the street of the
    shearers.
  </p>
  <p n="6">
    So were there many tales of the times that were, told on the pavement
    near the old green doors by the edge of the cobbled street, and the
    experience that the aged men had bought with their white hairs might
    be had cheap by the young. But from all their experience only this was
    clear, that never twice in their lives had she done the same infamous
    thing, and that the same calamity twice had never followed her goings.
    Therefore it seemed that means were doubtful and few for finding out
    what thing was about to befall; and an ominous feeling of gloom came
    down on the street of the ox-butchers. And in the gloom grew fears of
    the very worst. This comfort they only had when they put their fear
    into words—that the doom that followed her goings had never yet been
    anticipated. One feared that with magic she meant to move the moon;
    and he would have dammed the high tide on the neighbouring coast,
    knowing that as the moon attracted the sea the sea must attract the
    moon, and hoping by his device to humble her spells. Another would
    have fetched iron bars and clamped them across the street, remembering
    the earthquake there was in the street of the shearers. Another would
    have honoured his household gods, the little cat-faced idols seated
    above his hearth, gods to whom magic was no unusual thing, and, having
    paid their fees and honoured them well, would have put the whole case
    before them. His scheme found favour with many, and yet at last was
    rejected, for others ran indoors and brought out their gods, too, to
    be honoured, till there was a herd of gods all seated there on the
    pavement; yet would they have honoured them and put their case before
    them but that a fat man ran up last of all, carefully holding under a
    reverent arm his own two hound-faced gods, though he knew well—as,
    indeed, all men must—that they were notoriously at war with the
    little cat-faced idols. And although the animosities natural to faith
    had all been lulled by the crisis, yet a look of anger had come into
    the cat-like faces that no one dared disregard, and all perceived that
    if they stayed a moment longer there would be flaming around them the
    jealousy of the gods; so each man hastily took his idols home, leaving
    the fat man insisting that his hound-faced gods should be honoured.
  </p>
  <p n="7">
    Then there were schemes again and voices raised in debate, and many
    new dangers feared and new plans made.
  </p>
  <p n="8">
    But in the end they made no defence against danger, for they knew not
    what it would be, but wrote upon parchment as a warning, and in order
    that all might know: <q><hi>The bad old woman in black ran down the street
    of the ox-butchers.</hi></q>
  </p>
</div>
